this is a Soviet-era song And what is
это ну советских врем песня А что за
Murka Well, this is Murka, you are my little Murka
Мурка Ну это Мурка ты мой мурёночек
Murka, you are my little kitten
Мурка ты мой котёночек
about the belly about the cat or
про живот про кота или
something No, well, in the southern regions of Russia
что Нет ну это в южных регионах России
it’s like
такое
Mozart Great Good afternoon, how are you
Моцарта Здорово Добрый день как у вас
doing I’m from Ukraine, the city of Khmelnitsky
дела Я из Украины город Хмельницкий Вы
Where are you from Siberia  It’s already morning in Irkutsk, it’s
откуда из Сибири Иркутск у нас уже утро
cool, you support the special operation, to be
вон прикольно спецоперацию
honest, I have a
поддерживаете честно говоря нейтрально
neutral attitude because I don’t understand politics, I understand. Do you know who Roman Zinin is? Roman Zinin, I don’t know, there was such a guy, he was also neutral, he didn’t really
он тоже нейтрально относился не совсем
understand politics, but there his
разбирался в политики Но там его
friend was forcibly conscripted by the military registration and enlistment office
знакомого насильно призвали военкомат
to send to Ukraine, he came to
чтобы отправить в Украину он пришёл в
Irkutsk Look at Roman Zinin,
Иркутске Посмотрите Роман Зинин
google it, he came to the training camp for these
загуглите пришёл на сборы вот этих
conscripts, he stood up, said no one will ever
призывников встал сказал никто никогда
go, everyone will go home, in short,
не поедет все поедут домой короче
he shot the military commissar, they didn’t see
застрелил военкома не видели
this video,
это виде
although
хотя
yes, about Zinin Well, we have such a surname,
да про Зинина Ну есть такая фамилия у
Zinin, which is quite famous, but about
нас Зинин довольно известная но про
Roman  I don’t know, to be honest, or
романа вот я не знаю честно говоря или
Ruslan, well, in short, Zinin
Руслан ну короче Зинин
Yes, you’ll tell me Nothing, but what are you
Да ещ расскажете Ничего а что же ты же
neutral, what can I tell you? You’re
нейтральный что тебе можно рассказать Ты
not interested in lithium. But we can. How do you
же не интересуешься литий А можем А вы
feel? And how do you feel? So
как относитесь А вы как относитесь так
if you don’t know anything, we’ll
если ты ничего не знаешь плити м мы
talk  if you are
поговорим если там тебя интересует
only interested in butterfly music there, for example, there is
только там музыка бабочки например там
mathematics and that’s it. But politics, no, no,
математика и всё А политика нет да нет
no, why am I not taking
ну почему я как бы ну не не принимаю
sides? Of course, I don’t
ничью сторону Конечно я слабенько
understand much, but maybe I can do something,
разбираюсь но вдруг что-нибудь смогу да
yes. Well, okay, then maybe you can, let’s
Ну хорошо давай так вдруг сможешь давай
try who’s to blame  the fact that Russia
попробуем кто виноват в том что Россия
attacked
напала на
Ukraine so now
Украину так сечас
wait for additional development for
подождите допу разви
this Ukraine After all, it’s not Zelensky
этой Украине Ведь так ну не Зеленский
Poroshenko Zelensky first Yanukovych
Порошенко Зеленский сначала Янукович
supported Bandera then Poroshenko
поддерживал бандеру потом Порошенко
drove around with him in cars and Zelensky
разъезжал с ним на машинах и Зеленский
just started to start a
как раз-таки уже это начал разводить
conflict with
конфликт с
Russia in the program
Россией в передаче
time
время
Iriy agree  Yani understand this My
ирий согласен Яни понимаете это Моё
childhood Joe Biden said that Trump
детство Джо байден сказал что Трамп
invaded Russia you understand this you
вторгся в Россию вы понимаете это ты
saw your window teen saw your Window Window
видел своё окно тин видел своё Окно Окно
Yes yes it’s morning for us I’m not talking about the morning I’m talking about the
Да да у нас утро Я не про утро Я про
window Well, have you seen the conditions in
окно дано Ну ты видел в каких условиях
which you have some  school or
это у вас какая-то школа или
what is it in general is it price
что это вообще это цен
x where do they come to study? Well, it’s a budget
х куда приходят заниматься Ну бюджетное
building, what do you want? Well, this is a chemistry classroom.
здание ну что вы хотите Ну это кабинет
Yes, no, why is this music, here’s piano
Да нет почему это музыка вот пиани
music, it all seemed to me that there were chemists.
музыка всё мне показалось что там химики
I mean, you’re a pianist, I understand what you
А то есть ты пианист понял как ты
think,
считаешь
Russia is a
вот Россия богатая
relatively rich country  yes Yes, why in a
страна относительно да Да почему в
relatively rich country,
относительно богатой стране э
talented children study music in
талантливые дети занимаются музыкой в
relatively poor buildings
относительно бедных зданиях
like this? Well, in Russia there are two
таких Ну ведь в России есть же ведь два
types of buildings: budget ones and
типа зданий которые бюджетные и которые
private ones. If I went to a private
частные Если бы я пошёл в частную
music school, then this wouldn’t
музыкальную школу то там бы такого не
be there, but this is a budget music school
было а это бюджетная музыкальная
schools they are being built all over the country, dachas are
школа они строятся по всей стране дачно
blowing from such otso materials Well,
дут из таких отсо материалов Ну сами
look for yourself, like, well, well, what is this? Look,
Посмотрите ну типа ну ну что это Смотри
let me do this Russia sells oil, gas,
я а давай так Россия продаёт нефть газ
gold,
золото
diamonds, sells a huge amount Yes, it
алмазы продаёт огромное количество Да
sells, the same money goes to the budget
продаёт эти же деньги идут в бюджет
True, I think they go more  in the
Правда они Я думаю больше они идут в
budget for the army and for humanitarian
бюджет на армейские и на гуманитарную
aid
помощь
and not for construction and
а не на строительство и
improvement, that is, it turns out
облагораживание то есть получается
that Russia sells a huge
что Россия продаёт огромнейшее
amount of
количество
resources to different countries
ресурсов в разные страны
Yes The money goes to the budget but
Да Деньги идут в бюджет но
this budget does not reach music schools
до школ музыкальных не доходит этот
Yes, almost all budget
бюджет так Да практически всех бюджетных
institutions reach it A small part of the budget is
учреждениях доходит Малая часть бюджета
a question  attention question sir
вопрос внимание вопрос сри
small Czech Republic in which there is no oil gas
маленькую Чехию в которой нет нефти газа
diamonds so it does not sell hydrocarbons to the whole world
алмазов так она не продаёт всему миру
there but
там
budget schools there somehow look
бюджетные школы как-то выглядят иначе
a little different why in the Czech Republic which has a
немножко иначе Почему в Чехии в которой
much smaller budget than the
бюджета намного намного меньше чем
Great Mighty resource Russia the Czech Republic
Великой могучей ресурсной России Чехия
still pays money to others there  countries for
ещё деньги там платит другим странам за
gas oil Yes and so on and why a
газ нефть Да и так дальше и почему
person in the Czech Republic when he plays
человек в Чехии когда он занимается
music he practices in better
музыкой он занимается в более хороших
conditions not even in better conditions But in
условиях даже не в более хороших А в
normal conditions and not in such conditions Like
нормальных условиях а не в таком Как
you I think you know why Czech Republic Yes you
ты Я думаю Знаете почему Чехия Да вы
said correctly the Czech Republic is  a very
правильно сказали Чехия - это очень
rich country, but I think you know that
богатая страна но я думаю Знаете что
there are simply very few budgetary
там просто очень мало бюджетных
institutions there,
учреждений
that is, look, we have them being built
то есть смотрите у нас они строятся по
throughout the country and they are budgetary, that is, you
всей стране и то они бюджетные то есть
need to invest a lot of money there. And
там надо очень много денег вкладывать А
in the Czech Republic, I think there are more private
в Чехии Я думаю больше частных
entrepreneurs who are supported by
предпринимателей которых поддерживает
the state, for example
государство например
taxes there  reduces on them Well, in my opinion, it
налоги там на них снижает Ну по-моему
was somehow good. I understood correctly.
так как-то было хорошо Я правильно понял
I understood correctly that in the small Czech Republic,
Я правильно понял что маленькой Чехии у
which has no
которой нету
resources, the population has
ресурсов у населения
much more because there the population
намного больше потому что там население
can afford private teachers, but
может позволить себе частных учителей А
in Russia they cannot afford. Yes, not
в России не может позволить Да не
private. I mean  in general, a private
частные В смысле вообще частная
organization private schools Well, someone
организация частные школы Да ну кто-то
pays these private schools for
платит же этим частным школам за
tuition Yes, these same residents who
обучение Да эти самые жители которые
work for these means the residents
работают на этих значит у жителей
get money from somewhere in such
откуда-то берутся деньги в таком
quantities that they can still pay a
количестве что они могут ещё заплатить
private owner yes
частнику да
yes yes Okay, why in the Great  Russia
да да Хорошо а почему в Великой России
has no money in the budget, nor does
так ни в бюджете нет денег ни вот у
such a talented guy like you have the
такого талантливого парня как ты нету
money for his parents to
денег чтобы вот у его родителей чтобы в
go to a private school with normal
частную школу пойти с нормальным
repairs, so go to a private
ремонтом так пойти в частную
school, because we have very few
школу так потому что у нас очень мало
private schools, most often budget ones, you know
частных школ чаще всего бюджетные знаете
why Because  that we have a very weak
почему Потому что у нас очень слабая
policy in terms of supporting
политика в плане поддержки
entrepreneurs Well, in my opinion, it’s something
предпринимателей Ну по-моему так как-то
like we have high taxes tax on
что у нас типа большие налоги налог на
tax there tax on tax on tax on
налог там налог на налог на налог на
tax come on
налог давай
like this Why, for example, a
так Почему например
teacher in your budget
преподавательница вот в твоей бюджетной
school won’t open her own
школе не откроет свою
school What  tell me why the
школу Что говорите почему вот
teacher who teaches you in a
преподаватель который Учит тебя в
budget school will not open his own. You know
бюджетной школе не откроет свою Знаешь
why? Because there are no people who
почему Потому что нет у людей которые у
will be her clients because of
неё будут клиентами потому что
the solvency of the population. You will go
платежеспособность населения Ты пойдёшь
to her paid school, you won’t go.
к ней в платную школу не пойдёшь
Yes, because why would I study in a
Да потому что зачем я буду учиться в
paid school with a good  repairs When I
платной школе с хорошим ремонтом Когда я
can study in a free school and with
могу учиться в бесплатной школе да с
poor repairs, but you can
плохим ремонтом но на это можно же
somehow ignore it oh so
как-то не обращать внимания угу так
good, so let's go back to the Czech Republic, why then
хорошо так вернёмся к Чехии почему тогда
in the Czech Republic if you say that there are
в Чехии если ты говоришь что там это
just a lot of private ones Then why do
просто много частных Тогда почему Там
people study in private ones there  schools with good
люди учатся в частных школах с хорошим
repairs somehow need to be addressed, but I can’t
ремонтом как-то обращать вот не могу
understand it in front of
понять при
everyone, it’s possible because you know in the Czech Republic
всех возможно потому что знаете в Чехии
there’s a completely different morality, so to speak. It’s
там вообще другая так сказать
impossible that
нравственность Там невозможно чтобы
there’s just often a really cultural society there,
безредко там реально культурное общество
like they saw there, look,
типа вот они увидели там вот смотрите у
we recently had this incident  In general,
нас недавно такой был этот казус В общем
we have a five-story house and there, in general, they
у нас дом пятиэтажный и там в общем это
threw it off for Repairing the entrance, repairing the
скидывали на Ремонт подъезда чинили
tiles of the driveway, so there’s the floor of the house, they
плитку подъездную так там пол дома они
just don’t chip in, I
просто да мы не будем скидываться я
think it also depends on the lack of
думаю это ещё зависит от недостатка
funds and on the reluctance of people
денежных средств и от нежелания людей
to get together, and look, look, I
собраться и вот смотрите Смотри я
understood correctly  I correctly understood that in the
правильно понял Я правильно понял что в
Czech Republic they don’t allow the Czechs to allow
Чехии чехам они не позволяют себе чтобы
their children to study, yes,
ихние дети учились да
but the Russians allow their children to
Да а русские позволяют что вот дети
study music in such
занимались музыкой вот в таких
conditions. It turns out that yes, I understand.
условиях Получается что так да понял
Cool Why is this so and how can it
Прикольно А почему так и как это
be changed?
Изменить
Do you see we have such a mentality?
можно видите ли у нас такой менталитет
that we turn a blind eye to unpleasant
то что мы закрываем глаза на неприятные
conditions so as not to spend our money, but
условия чтобы не тратить свои деньги а
what is our money if it’s in the budget? That
какие свои деньги если они в бюджете То
is, you can say, look, let’s
есть можно сказать смотрите Давайте
not fire a missile at Ukraine, but
может не ракету по Украине выпустим так
repair the music
а отремонтируй музыкальную
school, but you shouldn’t have said a missile at Ukraine, I
школу а вот ракету по Украине Вы зря
condemn, I condemn Well, look Luda
сказали осуждаю осуждаю Ну смотри Люде
Well, yes, look, it’s your money, that
Ну так да Смотри это же ваши деньги то
is, instead of giving you
есть вместо того чтобы сделать Вам
normal conditions, you stopped
нормальный условия так и Вы перестали
living and studying in Yes, they are firing a missile at
жить в учиться в Да выпускают ракету по
Ukraine, well, this was done in order to
Украине ну это сделано же для того чтобы
rid Russia
избавить Россию
of
от
influence. I didn’t understand the question again. Well,
влияния Не понял ещё раз вопрос Ну
look at  it turns out that the
смотрите у у вас получается там
Nazis are developing there, so that is, the
развиваются нацисты так то есть
state is not doing anything with them at all.
государство с ними вообще ничего не
I understood correctly. I
делает сри Я правильно понял Я правильно
understood correctly that you, sitting in Irkutsk at this
понял что ты Сидя в Иркутске в этой
school, are like, yes, you are telling
школе такой да ты рассказываешь в
some kind of Nazis in Ukraine. I
Украине какие-то нацист Я правильно
understood correctly. And you in Ukraine,
понял А ты в Украине
listen to the Nazis to us  conveyed Well, in the
нацистов послушайте нам передавали Ну в
sense they conveyed to us. Of course, I know
смысле нам передавали Конечно я знаю то
that you have a negative attitude towards the transmission of
что вы негативно относитесь к передаче
information on Channel One. But damn,
информации по Первому каналу Но блин
still, these videos where crowds of people
всё-таки эти видео где идут толпы людей
with swastikas are walking and throwing red torches, there are
со свастика и бросают красные факелы там
monuments to Soviet heroes being burned in the square,
на площадь сжигают памятники Советским
this of course suggests Not
героям это конечно наталкивает на Не
very  nice where they burned it in the Monument to
очень приятные где сожгли в Памятник
Soviet Heroes in which city? Yes,
советским Героям в каком городе Да по
all over the country of Ukraine now they are just living,
всей стране Украине сейчас просто живут
they are breaking desecration of monuments, not only
ломают осквернять памятники не только
advice. Come on, so you watch your
совет Давай так ты смотришь свой первый
first channel. Yes, I watch the First Channel. Yes, there
Да смотрю Первый канал Да там там
they tell how life has become better in Russia
рассказывают Как в России лучше стало
and so on they continue to
жить и так дальше
tell no.  they talk about what is
рассказывают нет рассказывают о том что
happening in Ukraine, not Well, look,
делается на Украине не Ну вот смотри до
before the start of the war, he directly says that the
до начала войны прям рассказывает что
economy is growing there, we are
там растёт экономика там мы тамми
strong there, and so on.
сильные и так дальше
No, they talked a lot about
Да нет очень много рассказывали про
the coronavirus And how many people died and the fact
коронавирус И сколько умерло людей и то
that a vaccine was invented Okay, let’s do it
что изобретена вакцина Хорошо давай так
on Channel One  They once told you
по Первому каналу тебе рассказывали
that there are problems in that
когда-то что есть проблемы в том что
Russian children study in schools that still have the
российские дети учатся в школах ещё
old Soviet type of
старого советского такого
renovation. Yes, they told you and they
ремонта Да рассказывали и там что-то
promised something that Putin would give money for
обещали то что Путин выдаст деньги на на
it to be repaired and what
то чтобы вот отремонтировали и что
he gave Well, there was a lot on Channel One
выдал Ну по Первому каналу очень много
Well, all sorts of interviews when we walked
было Ну всяких вот интервью когда ходили
through such remote places and looked for
по таким глубинка и искали вот
subordinate schools. Well, they found them and took
подчиненные школы Ну находили брали
interviews. Can you show me in general
интервью А можешь мне показать вообще ну
how the interior of this school in which
как интерьер этой школы в которой
these musical instruments are used that
инструменты вот эти музыкальные на
you
котором ты
study? Well, you can say, you know,
учится Ну это можно сказать знаете
these are the
таковы
T lockers. Well, I wouldn’t  he said that here, you
Т шкафчики Ну я бы не сказал что здесь
know, you will have it, I’m sure you’re turning the sun
прям знаете ли у вас будет я уверен ВС
so quickly, my head
так быстро крутишь у меня ж голова
is spinning,
крутится
Nenya, and the toilet is somewhere on the
неня а туалет а туалет где-то там на
street.
улице
Yes, why do you think we’re even
Да Почему же вы что думаете мы вообще
in the woods? Well, I don’t know. Where’s the toilet?
чтоли в дерев Ну я не знаю А где туалет
you toilet
вас туалет
uh Okay And what kind of musical instrument do you
э Окей А инструмент у тебя музыкальный
have? They bought Yaha a new one for the
получается Яха новый закупали для
music school, no matter what And Yaha
музыкальной школы хоть на что А Яха -
is whose Japanese Yes, Japanese instrument
это чей японский Да японский инструмент
And what about Russian pianos that don’t work?  for
А что русские пианино не идут ну я не
pianists, the
школы этот этаж чисто для пианистов
next floor will be for trumpeters,
следующий этаж будет для трубачей
violinists Why exactly did they buy a Yamaha? This is
скрипачей Почему именно Ямаху купили вот
how they
как По какому принципу
were chosen? Because in Russia, most often
выбирали потому что в России чаще всего
when they prepare a child for concerts,
когда готовят ребёнка к концертам
especially a pianist, and there they put up
особенно у пианиста а там ставят
Yamaha pianos because
получается рояли именно Яха потому что
they are the most difficult to control the sound and
на них сложнее всего управлять звуком и
so that the child
чтобы ребнок
learns  There, in general, I’m now
научился Там в общем это вот я сейчас
going to play one
сыграю одну
note, you hear, yes, it really hits
ноту слышите вот да она прям бьёт по
the ears. Well, the sound. By the time it gets here, it
ушам Да ну звук Пока дойдёт сюда она уже
doesn’t hit much anymore, I think, well, I Mach, it
не сильно бьёт я думаю ну я Маха она
hits the ears very hard. But now I
очень сильно бьёт по ушам А вот я сейчас
’ll sit on the Russian piano.  in the class there
сяду на русское пианино У нас в классе
is also a Russian piano, now
тоже есть русское пианино вот сейчас
I’m sitting
сяду
down, it’s deaf. Yes, the thing is, as the teachers explain to us, that we need to learn to control the sound on all types of instruments, one more thing Wait, there are some holes in
одно Подожди а сверху какие-то дырки в
the ceiling on top. What is this, I don’t have something
потолке Это что такое бы я что-то не
caught up It was the old wiring here, but
догнал Это здесь была старая проводка но
you see it was removed. And when it was removed,
её сняли видите А когда её сняли
I don’t know where they removed it, but they installed a
я не знаю куда её сняли но установили
new one, you see, but what kind of holes I can’t
новую видите так а что за дырки я не
understand, well, these are the holes on which
понять ну это дырки на которых держалась
the wiring was held. You see, these ones are there, after all, they
проводка Видите вот вот эти там же ведь
drill first and  then they insert No,
сначала сверлят а потом вставляют Нет
this is And there were such round holes And
так это А такие круглые дыры там были А
this is a fire alarm Yes, these are these
это пожарная сигнализация Да вот вот эти
or something Nope Well, close-up Show
что ли нене А ну крупным планом Покажи
there a row of such holes was going Well, move
там ряд таких дырок шёл А ну отодвинь
the camera away
камеру что да вот
whatever Dezha lamp they just moved it above the
ни Дежа лампа просто её переставили выше
lamp and like that  there was a row of these holes, in my opinion,
лампо и вот так пошл ряд по-моему этих
no higher than
дырок не выше
the lamp above la yes, here is the hole hole Yes the
лампы выше ла да вот вот дырка дырка Да
base Yes here
основа Да вот
it is Yes Well, I’m saying
э Вот это да Ну я же говорю Здесь
This is where the wiring was kept I think you can
держалась это проводка Я думаю видите
even see this and in short, they changed it a long time ago,
даже это и короче давно поменяли
not recently, quite simply, they didn’t cover it up, they
не недавно довольно просто не замазали
didn’t paint it over  You see how
не закрасили Поня видите как
Yes, somehow we
Да вот как-то так у нас
understood what was
понял у вас там что
going on there. It’s normal too. But this blue thing
творится Нормально тоже А вот это синее
in the back is a door or something, I still
сзади это дверь или что-то я так и не
can’t understand that it’s blue.
могу понять что это синее
And we decorated this as a class for the New Year,
А это мы классом украшали к Новому году
but take it off  - we just can’t. We can’t
но снять что-то никак не можем Руки не
reach it. We’ve decorated it. Well, it’s raining like this. And what to take it off, take it, tear it off, tear
что его снять возьми дёрни это оторви
it all off and it’s attached there with tape, we
его всё а он прикреплён там на скотч мы
specially fixed it well, so
его специально хорошо закрепили поэтому
we have to climb to tear it off; we don’t have time;
это надо лезть отдирать нам некогда
in short, I understand. What are you
короче понял А ты что
playing? Well  they give us classical
играешь Ну нам дают классические
works here
произведения вот
Morta and you it’s already morning what
Морта а ты это у вас уже утро сколько
time is it It’s 4:00 in the morning here
времени У нас сейчас 4:00 утра
Yes That is, did you come to school at 4:00 in the morning
да То есть ты в 4:00 утра пришёл в
or have you not left school yet no
школу или ты ещё не уходил со школы нет
in general this is how we are located  Our
у нас в общем так расположено у нас
hostel is very close to the school,
общежитие очень близко рядом со школой
you know, yeah right now I,
понимаете Угу зараз сейчас я
well, well, and this school is open every
ну-ну и эта школа она открыта каждый
day. That’s realistic, but there’s a guard sitting there and you
день Вот реально но там сидит вахтёр и
need to show your pass so that he can give you the key,
нужно показать пропуск чтобы он дал ключ
and that’s where people even come to study at 3:00 in the morning, can you
и это туда люди даже в 3:00 ночи
imagine?  It
приходят заниматься представляете Ага у
says to me that it’s 5:00 a.m. in Irkutsk
меня пишет что в Иркутске сейчас 5:00
Well, 4330 Oops,
утра Ну так 4330 Опа как
in short, okay, look, I don’t
по Короче ладно О'кей то смотри Э я не
understand, that is, you came to
понял то есть ты получается пришёл ночью
work out at night Well, it’s early in the morning Yes,
позаниматься Ну это раннее утро Да а
why? So what exactly is not allowed during the day or
почему Так ну что именно днём нельзя или
in  Bad evening I have a class, look at
в бед вечером у меня занятие смотрите у
my class at 8:30 That’s why I’m always
меня занятие 8:30 Поэтому я всегда
used to going to bed, you know,
привык ложиться знаете
at 7 because it’s kind of
так в 7 потому что у нас как бы уже
getting dark here in general, why do you
темнеет вообще жесть се чего в се вечера
really go to bed every evening Yes, and you get up, I get up at
ложишься спать реально Да так а встаёшь
three o’clock, you go to
три идёшь в
school  play until what time do you
школу играть до какого ча
play? Well, I play until 6. Then I go
играешь Ну вот я играю до 6 Потом иду
there and get dressed and go to school at 8 am. There’s
там одеваюсь и в школу на 8 утра там
a class there. It’s
занятие
cool. You’re in the dormitory. Yes, that’s
Прикольно Это ты в общежитии Да этом
what, what are you in the dormitory? You live
ь что что ты в общежитии да Живёшь
here? Yes, nearby, that is, you yourself are not from
этом Да рядом то есть ты сам не с
Irkutsk, but where?  something from the region Yes, I’m from the region
Иркутска а где-то из области Да родом
Yes, I came
Да я приехал
from the region from the village Yes, there
из области из деревни Да
was some kind of bad situation there, I
какой-то да там у нас вообще худа было я
understood,
понял
yes And you have gas in your village,
да А газ у вас в деревне
yes there is gas, there is Internet,
есть да газ Интернет есть
after all, Russia is not such a rotten
всё всё-таки Россия не такая загни
country as you think  Well, somehow
страна как вы думаете Ну как-то
yes And you can play the Ukrainian anthem
да А ты гимн Украины можешь
that you can play Ukraine, but I do
сыграть что Украины умеешь сыграть а я т
n’t know And you don’t pick it up and don’t
не знаю А так не подбираешь на и не
fumble yet
шаришь ещё
Yes, I
Да понял я
just realized and Chervona Kolyna that what
только а Червона колына что что
[music]
[музыка]
you can
можеш
now this  Hava
сейчас это Хава
Nagila Hava
нагила Хава
Nagila This is Amurka in the sense of what kind of Murka
Нагила Это амурка в смысле какая Мурка
I say Hava Nagila e
говорю Хава Нагила э
song Yes no hangi This is probably
песня Да нет ханги Это наверно
Rka this is a Soviet era song And what kind of
рка это ну советских врем песня А что за
Murka Well this is Murka you are my Murka
Мурка Ну вот это Мурка ты мой мурёночек
Murka you are my little kitten
Мурка ты мой котёночек
about the belly about the cat or
про живот про кота или
something No, this is it  in the southern regions of Russia
что Нет ну это в южных регионах России
this was sung. And why didn’t I just hear
такое пелось А что я просто не слышал
it, well little muryonochka Kitten And then
его ну мурёночек Котёночек А дальше
Forgive my beloved, this is
Прости любимая любима это что романс
some kind of romance or
какой-то или
something like a romance Yes, it’s cool, I haven’t
что по типу романса Да прикольно не
heard such a
слышал такой
song, this is one of these, the black cat gang
песни это из этих вот банда чёрная кошка
was not in the Soviet Union  heard No,
была в Советском Союзе не слышали Нет
it was just from this that
это как раз таки из этой
you and Tony burned for me You wanted to play
горили ты мне с Тони Ты захотел сыграть
not Murka, but precisely Murka and not
не Мурку а именно Мурку а не
Mozart Yes, I
Моцарта Да
can Murka I thought she could be said to
могу Мурка Я думал она можно сказать
unite
объединяет
peoples like it was the Soviet Union in
народы типа это же был Советский Союз
the sixties and like when everyone knew the ethos
шестидесятые и типа когда все знали этус
I’m an hour
Я час
under  Roulette met
под рулетке встречались
Kazakhs and Tajiks They really recognized this
казахи таджики Они реально узнавали эту
song and sang along Cool And there are
песню подпевали Прикольно А других
no other Soviet songs left that
советских песен не осталось которые
can not be sung
могут подпеть
Why Ogonyok but I don’t know the notes, too,
не Почему Огонёк но ноты не знаю тоже
what kind of
что за
Ogonyok Well, in the position the
Огонёк Ну вот На позиции
girl
девушка
saw off the fighter I don’t know but Katyusha maybe you
провожала бойца не знаю а Катюша может
know Katyusha there apple trees toys This is
Катюшу знаешь там яблони игруши Вот это
we
мы
don’t know the notes And what are you studying, you
ноты не знаю А это что ты учишься ты в 4
come to school at 4 am, you don’t
утра приходишь в школу ноты не
know the notes, I don’t know the notes, but you don’t know, what are
знаешь ноты не знаю но ты не зна а что ж
you doing, what are you doing in the
ты делаешь че
morning, you come at 4 am and
утра ты приходишь в 4 утра и в че
are sitting there at school at che roulette, so Ino
рулетке сидишь там в школе поэтому Ино
you don’t
ты не
you know, that's what you named individual songs And
знаешь так вы назвали отдельные песни А
I play entire large
я играю целые большие
works, I understood for example
произведения понял например
Which
Какие
Rachmaninoff Roman you haven't heard no Well,
Рахманинова Роман не слышали нет А ну
let's oh I
давайте
hope your phone doesn't explode, I'm
о Надеюсь у вас телефон не взорвётся я
not through the phone, I'm like that
не через телефон я так че
[music]
[музыка]
[applause]
[аплодисменты]
but tell me the Ukrainian ones  The
а назовите мне украинских Композиторов
main composers are you and
глн а Вы да
I’ve been talking to all this time And you’re like you
я разговаривал с всё это время А вы типа
’re afraid of the Russians
Боитесь русских
No fob well that’s being afraid of fear And
Нет фоб ну это же бояться боязнь А
what does Russian have to do with I didn’t say that I’m a Russian
причём русский Я же не сказа что я
fob You’re afraid of Russia itself, not me I’m afraid of the
фоб Боитесь самой России не я ру Я боюсь
Russ That is, if the ancestors of the
Русов То есть если вот приедет предки
ancients come  Ukrainians Yes Russians I'm afraid of them
древних украинцев Да Русы Я их боюсь Вот
If I saw Prince Vladimir now
если бы сейчас я увидел князя Владимира
I'd be scared of him and the Russians What they're afraid of
я его испугался а русских Что боятся
Not bad not bad Interesting
Неплохо неплохо Интересный
person and how do you feel about Rakhmanino Well, I
человек а как рахманино вы относитесь Ну
listened to him Well what about music
вот слушал его Ну что относится музыка
is
есть
music But the fact that He escaped from the
музыка А вот то что Он сбежал из
Soviet Union and  You can do the Moonlight Sonata
Советского Союза а Лунную сонату сможете
Well, I can play a little bit
сделать Ну так чуть-чуть могу наиграть
Let's
Давайте
[music]
[музыка]
wait wait wait wait something
подожди подожди почекай подожди чтото
seems to me
мне кажется
[music]
[музыка]
out of tune thank you thank you Say It
фальшиви спасибо спасибо Говорите Мне
seems to me that there was a
кажется что с фальшиви там было
transition from out of tune And I wanted to make a transition from
переход А я хотел сделать переход из
Moonlight Sonata to Lizzie  you understand, yes yes Well,
Лунной санаты в лизи вы поняли да да Ну
it’s not a turn in, it just started and
вот вот не перел вот как раз началось и
some kind of confusion turned out to know
какой-то сумбур получился зна не и
Nelya Yes, I’m
Нели Да
disappointed, I agree, just like you did Russia.
разочаровал согласен прям как вы Россию
And you can, like Zelensky, play the piano
А ты можешь как Зеленский на рояле
like this clown or something?
сыграть как этот клоун что ли Да
Yes, yes, how he was a clown  there you can play like this,
вот да как он был клоуном там можешь так
he played with his fingers,
сыграть он оди пальцами
played with his fingers, and
играл оди пальцами да
even
прям ногой ещё
got it right with his foot, take Google Zelensky plays the
доставал возьми загугли Зеленский играет
piano
на рояле
Then you will amaze me, you will give me away, you
Потом ты будешь пораж мне вы мне выдаст
know that there are no pigs If you Googled, I’m
знаете что свиней нет Если ты загугли я
telling you, if you
тебе говорю если ты
Google Zelensky plays the piano, you will
загугли Зеленский играет на рояле ты
start to come to  3 hours for these
начнёшь приходить в 3 часа на эти
rehearsals
репетиции
and you’ll play Bella Ciao
так а Белла Чао сыграешь
that you’ll play Bella Ciao
что Белла Чао сыграешь
[music]
[музыка]
that’s what there is such a lie that there is no well in a
вот что есть такого вру что нет ну в
normal person in an ordinary person you
нормальном человеке в обычном вы
hate just talk and
ненавидите просто раси и
listen to everything
всё слушай
Why do Russians live
Почему русские живут
in and rejoice at the fact that missiles are flying to
в и радуется того что ракеты летят на
Ukraine because  that even though we are
Украину потому что хоть мы и
alive, we will not allow Nazism to develop
живём мы не позволим нацизму развиваться
Let's send a couple to
Давайте отправим паро на
Kiev
Киев
Yes, how do you see your future,
Да как ты видишь своё будущее
I will go to fight
я пойду воевать
against how do you see your
против как ты видишь своё
future, let's pose the question differently
будущее давай не так поставлю вопрос
When you finish your studies and can no longer live
Когда ты отучишься и уже не сможешь жить
in a hostel, what
в общежитии что дальше
will happen next I will  I will give private Rockies,
будет я буду давать частные Роки буду
accompanists in bars will
концертмейстеров барах меня будут
invite me. And if Ukraine calls me, I will
приглашать А если меня позовёт Украина я
refuse and say that I am a patriot. That
откажусь и скажу то что я патриот То
is, you will give private lessons in
есть ты будешь давать частные уроки в
schools that don’t exist, because no one
школах которых нет да потому что никто
takes private lessons there. You will play
частные уроки там не берёт будешь играть
in bars. That is, you  I studied in order
в барах это То есть ты учился для того
to play in bars, yes Yes,
чтобы играть в барах именно да Этим Да
yes, yes, I understood, I will play for Russians and
да да понял я буду играть для русских а
not for fun
не для прикольно
Thank you Thank you, I tried,
Спасибо Спасибо я старался
what else,
что ещё
tell me, I understood why you
раскажите я понял почему ты Мурку
are studying Murka
изучаешь
because
потому
no one needs Liza or Lunar Sanata there
что Лизе или Лунная саната там никому не
And this is sadly
нужна И это печально
true  lizy and smart sanata are needed for
правда лизи и умная саната нужны для
private lessons and this is quite insignificant.
частных уроков и Это довольно неча То
That is, it turns out that I understand correctly that
есть получается я правильно понимаю что
musicians in Russia teach classical
музыканты в России учат классическую
music in order to teach others
музыку для того чтобы учить других
classical
классической
music, why
музыке почему же
aren’t there a lot of concerts here? There are concerts
нет здесь очень много концертов даётся
about You probably haven’t heard about this
о Вы наверное не слышали о таком
interesting A  you know Wanda Lando is a
интересно А вы знаете ванду Ландо это
Ukrainian pianist No, I haven’t
украинская пианист Нет не
heard of it, so she left Ukraine and
слышал так вот она покинула Украину и и
moved to Russia because in Russia she is
перешла в Россию потому что в России ей
better than in Ukraine Cool And where did
лучше чем в Украине Прикольно А откуда
she come from, what city did she move from in
она с какого города переехала в
Russia, she came from Dnepr and as I
России она приехала из Днепра и я так
understand it, To Irkutsk Yes  that she came to Irkutsk,
понял В Иркутск Да что в Иркутск
why not to Moscow And there she
приехала почему нет в Москву И там
began her concert
начала свою концертную
activity What was the name of the village
деятельность Как называлась деревня
Where did you come from to Irkutsk
Откуда ты приехал в Иркутск
fly write on th instag I don’t know why this is
муха пись на й instag Я не знаю для чого
for what there is to marvel at the office
це тоб Для чего то там дивитись на офес
and for you one two and three clicks a  you're the
а для тебе один два а три клика а ты
best for me and I'll be there for me A bunch of
тримае мене и я буду к в мене там Купа
fouls and I'll be the best for
фолов и в мене буде класний настр щоб
you
так давай я тебя чекаю